In 1970,
1970 年
Taiwan's foreign trade
台 灣 的 對 外 貿 易
enjoyed a trade surplus for the first time.
首 次 出 現 盃 餘
Major export products included
出 口 項 目 中
electronics, plastics, and machinery,
主 要 是 電 子 ， 塑 膠 與 機 械 產 品
as the focus of industrial development
國 內 的 產 業 發 展 重 心
in Taiwan transformed gradually.
已 經 逐 步 轉 型
Although economic growth
同 時 經 濟 成 長
had exceeded 11 percent
也 已 經 連 續 四 年
for four years running,
超 過 百 分 之 十 一
the international situation was starting
但 是 國 際 政 治 情 勢
to undergo tremendous changes.
開 始 發 生 重 大 的 變 化
As a series of
迎 接 台 灣 的
diplomatic setbacks
是 一 連 串
befell Taiwan,
驚 濤 駭 浪 般 的 外 交 挫 敗
the history of the Taiwan people
台 灣 人 民 的 歷 史
again underwent dramatic changes.
又 有 了 非 常 戲 劇 性 的 發 展
On Oct. 25, 1971,
1971 年 10 月 25 日
Albania proposed draft resolution No. 2758,
由 阿 爾 巴 尼 亞 所 提 的
calling for the admission of the PRC and expulsion
接 納 北 京
of the representatives of Chiang Kai-shek from the U.N.
排 除 蔣 政 府 的 2758 號 提 案
As the draft resolution was put to vote,
在 聯 合 國 正 式 付 諸 表 決
then foreign minister Chou Shu-kai,
中 華 民 國 外 交 部 長 周 書 楷
knowing the vote result in advance,
由 於 預 知 表 決 的 結 果
announced Taiwan's withdrawal from the U.N.
趙 在 決 議 案 進 行 表 決 之 前
before the voting started.
自 行 宣 布 退 出 聯 合 國
Faced with such disastrous impact,
面 對 如 此 重 大 的 衝 擊
Chiang Kai-shek in his address to the nation
蔣 介 石 發 表 告 全 國 同 胞 書
denounced the U.N. General Assembly
嚴 厲 指 賁 聯 合 國 大 會
for undermining the U.N. Charter and principles.
自 毀 露 章 的 宗 旨 與 原 則
Government agencies and the media also
並 且 透 過 政 府 機 關 與 媒 體
joined in protest activities
共 同 發 起 的 抗 議 活 動
throughout Taiwan.
也 在 台 灣 陸 續 舉 行
In February 1972,
1972 年 2 月
U.S. President Nixon visited the PRC.
美 國 總 統 尼 克 森 草 問 中 國
The U.S. and the PRC jointly issued
雙 方 共 同 發 表 上 海 聯 合 公 報
the Shanghai Communiqué, which once again upset
再 次 對 於 台 灣 的 國 際 處 境
the international status of Taiwan.
產 生 極 大 的 震 撼
Our two peoples tonight
今 晚 我 們 兩 國
hold the future of the world in our hands.
將 世 界 的 未 來 掌 握 在 我 們 手 中
And as we think about the future,
而 且 所 要 怒 考 的 未 來
we are dedicated to a principle that
就 是 致 力 於 建 立 一 個 新 世 界
we can build a new world, a world of peace,
一 個 和 平 的 世 界
a world of justice,
一 個 正 義 的 世 界
a world of independence...
以 及 使 所 有 國 家 獨 立 的 …
Withdrawal from the U.N.
退 出 聯 合 國
adversely affected
對 台 灣 外 交 發 展 與 國 際 處 境
Taiwan's diplomatic relations and international status.
已 經 產 生 極 不 利 的 影 響
Pres. Nixon's visit to the PRC
尼 克 森 芝 問 中 國
further set in motion a series of events.
則 牽 動 更 大 的 後 續 效 應
The number of countries with diplomatic ties to Taiwan
承 認 台 灣 當 局 的 邦 交 國
gradually diminished.
逐 漸 減 少
Even Japan, once a major ally,
連 極 重 要 的 日 本
also severed ties with Taiwan
也 於 1972 年 9 月 29 日
on Sept. 29, 1972.
與 台 灣 斷 交
Before severing ties with Taiwan,
日 本 宣 布 與 台 灣 斷 交 之 前
Japan had sent special envoy Etsusaburo Shiina to Taiwan.
曾 經 派 特 使 椎 名 悅 三 郎 來 台
But his visit sparked off severe protests.
引 發 激 烈 的 抗 議 活 動
After Japan severed ties with Taiwan,
正 式 宣 布 斷 交 之 後
many Taiwan organizations initiated
台 灣 許 多 團 體 更 發 起
movements to boycott Japan;
各 式 各 樣 的 披 制 日 本 的 運 動
but these movements did not last long.
不 遇 並 未 持 久
Apart from setbacks in foreign relations,
除 了 外 交 困 局 之 外
Taiwan also experienced problems in economic growth
1970 年 代 初 期 的 台 灣 內 部
during the early 1970s.
也 出 現 經 濟 成 長 的 難 題
Statistics show that
據 統 計
the number of immigrants applying to leave Taiwan
1972 年 申 請 移 民 的 人 數
in 1972 increased eight-fold from previous years.
較 往 年 增 加 八 倍
In 1973,
1973 年
the Fourth Middle East War
第 四 次 中 東 戰 爭
resulted in the first oil crisis.
引 發 第 一 次 石 油 危 機
The decline of the world economy
全 球 的 經 濟 衰 退
was yet another blow to Taiwan,
對 於 靠 外 貴 起 家 的 台 灣
which was dependent on foreign trade.
又 造 成 一 次 重 大 的 震 撼
In the evening of April 5, 1975,
1975 年 4 月 5 日 夜 裡
Chiang Kai-shek, whose
威 權 統 治 台 灣
authoritarian rule of Taiwan lasted 25 years,
四 分 之 一 個 世 紀 的 蔣 介 石
passed away during this critical period.
就 在 這 樣 危 機 重 重 的 年 代 過 世
He left the difficult problems
把 難 題 留 給 了
to his son Chiang Ching-kuo and the people of Taiwan.
他 的 兒 子 蔣 經 國 和 台 灣 人 民
On the day following Chiang's death,
蔣 介 石 去 世 的 第 二 天
the government declared a month of mourning.
政 府 宣 布 全 國 進 入 國 喪 時 期
Students were taught songs in memory of Chiang.
全 國 學 生 被 教 唱 著 蔣 公 紀 念 歌
Employees in the military, government, and the academia
全 台 灣 的 軍 公 教 人 員
were asked to put on black armbands.
引 須 配 戴 喪 章 一 個 月
Flags in the military, government, and schools
各 部 隊 ， 機 關 ， 學 校
flew at half-mast for one month.
降 半 旗 致 含 一 個 月
Entertainment establishments were suspended for one month.
各 媧 樂 場 所 停 止 營 業 一 個 月
All newspapers were printed only in black and white.
所 有 報 紙 改 為 黑 白 印 刷
The three TV networks aired programs in black and white.
吟 播 放 黑 白 影
After the death of Chiang Kai-shek
蔣 介 石 的 去 世
and with strict government control,
在 嚴 厲 的 控 制 之 下
the whole nation was engulfed in an atmosphere of mourning.
全 國 共 同 陷 入 喪 禮 的 氣 氛 當 中
An old era has ended with Chiang's death.
一 個 舊 的 時 代 從 此 結 束
Yet the new era of Chiang Ching-kuo
但 是 另 一 個 新 的 蔣 經 國 時 代
also began.
隨 之 開 始
After the KMT government
其 實 早 在 國 民 黨 政 府
retreated to Taiwan from the mainland,
由 中 國 大 陸 退 守 台 灣 後
Chaing Kai-shek had started to groom
蔣 介 石 就 積 極 培 養
his son Chiang Ching-kuo as successor.
他 的 長 子 蔣 經 國 為 接 班 人
In 1949, Chiang Ching-kuo,
蔣 經 國 於 1949 年
under order of Chiang Kai-shek,
奉 蔣 介 石 的 命 令
was in charge of moving gold stocked in the mainland
負 貧 將 存 放 在 大 陸 的 黃 金
to Taiwan.
運 送 到 台 灣
In 1950, he became head of General Political Department
1950 年 擔 任 總 政 治 部 主 任
to control political affairs and intelligence work.
開 始 掌 握 政 工 與 情 治 系 統
He later became head of Veterans Affairs Commission,
之 後 擔 任 退 輔 會 主 委
a minister without portfolio
行 政 院 政 務 委 員
and defense minister.
國 防 部 部 長 等 職
In 1970, Chiang became vice premier,
1970 年 任 行 政 院 副 院 長
and in 1972, premier.
1972 年 擔 任 行 政 院 長
Chiang wielded absolute power.
蔣 經 國 全 面 掩 握 權 力
Having studied in Moscow
曾 經 在 莫 斯 科 留 學
and joined the Communist Party,
並 加 入 共 產 黨 的 蔣 經 國
Chiang, unlike his father,
顯 然 不 再 像 他 的 父 親 那 樣
was hot obsessed with retaking the mainland.
執 迷 於 反 攻 大 陸
He was more pragmatic
而 脊 以 較 務 實 的 態 度
in face of Taiwan's political environment.
來 面 對 台 灣 的 政 治 環 境
Chiang began to employ elite Taiwanese politicians
他 閘 始 起 用 台 籍 政 治 精 莢
such as Hsieh Tung-min, Lin Yang-kang,
如 謝 東 間 ， 林 洋 港
Lee Teng-hui, and Chiu Chuang-huan,
李 登 輝 ， 邱 創 煥 等 人
which was seen as the start of indigenization in Taiwan.
被 認 為 是 台 灣 本 土 化 的 開 始
On Dec. 16, 1973,
1973 年 12 月 16 日
Chiang Ching-kuo announced
蔣 經 國 正 式 提 出
a plan to complete the ten major infrastructure projects
將 在 五 年 之 內
within five years.
完 成 十 項 重 大 的 建 設
Finance and economic officials of mainland descent
外 省 籍 財 經 官 員
such as Li Kuo-ting, Yen Chia-kan,
如 李 國 鼎 ， 嚴 家 淦
and Sun Yun-syuan
孫 運 璿 等 人
were assigned this vital task
f8y 項
of Taiwan's economic transformation.
轉 塊 台 灣 經 濟 結 構 的 重 任
The successful completion of the ten major infrastructure
十 大 建 設 的 成 功 完 成
projects, along with the
配 合 當 時
gradual revival of the global economy,
國 際 經 濟 情 況 的 漸 趨 好 轉
enabled Taiwan to survive
不 僅 使 台 灣 安 然 度 遇
the first Oil Crisis
第 一 次 石 油 危 機
and facilitated the growth of Taiwan's economy.
也 使 台 灣 的 經 濟 蓬 勃 成 長
Local small and medium enterprises,
還 有 中 小 鈍 業 以 其 旺 盤 的 活 力
with their aggressiveness and flexible production methods,
與 靈 活 彈 性 的 生 產 方 式
started to gain prominence in the international market.
闖 入 國 際 市 場
Taiwan's production model based on dual economy
形 成 雙 元 經 濟 的 生 產 模 式
thus became a model for other developing countries.
成 為 開 發 中 國 家 發 展 的 典 範
To alleviate the resentment of local Taiwanese for
此 外 ， 為 了 紓 解 台 灣 人
being excluded from central government policy-making,
無 法 參 與 中 央 決 策 的 怨 氣
Chiang amended the Temporary Provisions during
蔣 經 國 透 過 修 改
the Period of Mobilization against Communist Rebellion
動 員 戴 亂 時 期 臨 時 條 款 的 方 式
and called for elections starting at the end of 1972
將 二 十 五 年 不 改 選 的 台 灣 國 會
for additional National Assembly representatives,
自 1972 年 底 起
who were frozen in office for the last 25 years.
開 放 增 額 中 央 民 意 代 表 選 舉
Although these newly
雖 然 這 些
elected representatives accounted for
台 灣 新 選 出 的 中 央 民 代
only a small minority in the National Assembly,
只 佔 國 會 總 額 的 極 小 部 分
the election paved the way
但 已 經 為 台 灣 的 民 主 運 動
for a new democratic movement in Taiwan.
多 提 供 了 一 條 跑 道
There was a heightened sense of awareness of
文 化 的 本 土 認 同
local cultures during Chiang's administration.
也 在 蔣 經 國 時 代 下 蓬 勃 發 展
In September 1973
1973 年 9 月
Cloud Gate Dance Theatre established by Lin Huai-min
由 林 懷 民 所 創 立 的 雲 門 舞 集
brought an all-new
開 始 帶 給 台 灣 一 個
cultural experience to Taiwan.
全 新 的 文 化 體 驗
Every performance
每 一 場 渡 出
attracted positive and enthusiastic feedbacks.
都 引 起 熟 烈 的 迴 響
In 1975,
1975 年
Yang Hsien, Hu Te-fu, and Li Shuang-tse
由 楊 弦 ， 胡 德 夫 ， 李 雙 澤 等 人
launched a folk song movement, as the start of
發 起 了 一 場 現 代 民 歌 運 動
a new era looking for the people's roots.
瞎 徵 一 個 尋 根 的 新 時 代 的 開 端
Singing one's own songs
唱 自 己 的 歌
became a fad among students,
成 為 當 時 學 生 的 流 行
bringing the popularization of folk songs in schools.
之 後 也 形 成 校 園 民 歌 的 風 潮
In addition, folk arts,
此 外 ， 出 自 民 間 的 藝 術
both traditional or contemporary,
不 管 是 傳 統 或 者 現 代
started to receive widespread attention
也 相 繼 在 台 灣 知 識 界
in local intellectual circles.
引 起 廣 泛 的 注 意 與 討 論
These are all results of efforts by cultural elites,
這 些 都 是 台 灣 的 文 化 精 莢
intellectuals, and young students who
知 識 分 子 和 青 年 學 生 們
recognized the importance of local culture.
認 真 思 考 自 我 文 化 認 同 的 結 果
Who are we?
到 底 我 們 是 誰
What is Taiwan?
台 灣 又 是 什 麼
Influenced by Chinese and U.S. cultures
在 大 中 國 文 化 與 美 國 文 化
for a quarter of a century, the people of Taiwan
影 響 四 分 之 一 個 世 紀 之 後
wanted to rediscover their lost identity.
台 灣 人 民 想 要 找 回 失 去 的 自 己
They cautioned repeatedly.
他 們 一 再 重 複 地 叮 噓
Do not forget.
不 要 忘 記
There is much hardship in the establishment
華 路 藍 縷
of a foundation.
以 啟 山 林
Native literature came into existence accordingly.
鄉 土 文 學 在 這 樣 的 育 景 下 產 生
A group of Taiwan-born young writers
一 批 本 土 出 身 的 青 年 作 家
started to write about the ordinary people around them
開 始 書 寫 自 己 周 邊 的 小 人 物
and their experiences growing up.
與 自 己 的 成 長 經 驗
They further criticized the
更 進 而 批 判
unfairness, unjustness, and absurdity in the island.
大 環 境 的 不 公 不 義 與 荒 謬
Following the Taiwan native literature movement,
接 續 鄉 土 文 學 的 薪 火
a wave of new Taiwan movies
八 十 年 代 風 起 雪 湧 的
proliferated in the 1980s.
台 灣 新 電 影 浪 潮
The movies criticized and provided introspection on
更 是 對 五 、 六 十 年 代
the mindset during the 1950s
傾 向 大 中 國
and 1960s, which gravitated
與 美 國 文 化 的 思 維 架 構
towards Chinese and American cultures.
提 出 了 批 判 和 反 省
The young movie-makers
年 輕 的 電 影 創 作 者
attempted to establish a
鈍 圖 建 構 出 一 個
new Taiwan experience and aesthetic concept.
全 新 的 台 灣 經 驗 和 美 學 觀 念
The movie The Sandwich Man
電 影 ﹁ 時 子 的 大 玩 偶 」
was an adaptation of a novel by Huang Chun-ming.
改 編 自 作 家 黃 春 明 的 原 著 小 說
It was an important collective work by the
這 是 戰 後 嬰 兒 潮 對 台 灣 經 驗
post-war baby boomers about the Taiwan experience.
集 體 創 作 的 重 要 作 品
The movie gained prominence in international film festivals.
引 來 世 界 各 大 影 展 的 重 視
Taiwan, the small island,
台 灣 ， 這 個 在 歷 史 的 發 展 中
lacking in identity throughout history,
始 終 缺 乏 主 體 性 的 小 島
finally received international attention
困 為 台 灣 新 電 影 運 動
because of the new movie movement.
恆 到 了 國 際 間 的 注 意
Apart from the diplomatic setbacks
1970 年 代
during the 1970s,
國 際 外 交 的 挫 折
the administration likewise
以 及 統 治 當 局
faced the prospect of power transition.
也 面 臨 權 力 移 轉 的 關 頭
The clamor for political reform
台 灣 社 會 開 始 醛 釀
started to brew
要 求 政 治 變 革 的 力 量
through student political discussions
一 條 是 透 過 大 學 雜 誌 的
in college magazines
書 生 論 政 路 線
and the emergence of Taiwan-born political figures
另 一 條 是 新 一 代 本 土 政 治 人 物
through local elections.
透 遇 選 舉 嵩 起
This resulted in civil movements
發 展 成 黨 外 民 運 路 線
by members of the opposition.
烏 黨 籍 的 反 對 運 動 人 士
After several elections,
經 由 數 次 的 選 舉
the movement gradually transformed
逐 漸 結 合 成 一 股
into a political opposition.
在 野 的 政 治 勢 力
In 1977,
1977 年
Taiwan for the first time
台 灣 首 次 舉 辦
held elections for five local offices.
五 項 地 方 公 職 人 員 選 舉
Hsu Hsin-liang, without KMT nomination, ran for the
沒 有 獲 國 民 黨 提 名 的 許 信 良
election for Taoyuan county magistrate on his own.
自 行 參 選 桃 園 縣 長
Hsu was subsequently expelled from the KMT,
困 而 被 國 民 黨 開 除 黨 籍
and became a member of the opposition.
成 為 黨 外 的 一 員
On Nov. 19, Election Day,
11 月 19 日 投 票 當 天
the supervisor of the 213
在 中 壞 市 的 213 號 投 開 票 所
ballot center in Chungli City
選 監 主 任 因 為 涉 嫌
allegedly tampered the
將 投 給 許 俸 良 的 選 票
ballots cast in favor of Hsu.
塗 抹 成 廢 票
The public filed complaints on the spot,
當 場 被 民 眾 舉 發
and conflict ensued between the two parties.
雙 方 發 生 衝 突
In the end, Hsu's supporters
最 後 支 持 許 俸 良 的 民 眾
surrounded the Chungli police station,
包 圍 中 壞 分 局
vandalized police cars,
搗 毀 警 車
and set fire to the police station.
並 放 火 焚 燒 警 察 局
This was the Chungli Incident, which had
爆 發 了 台 灣 民 主 化 運 動 過 程 中
significant impact on later democratic movements.
影 響 極 大 的 中 壞 事 件
The Chungli Incident was the first time
中 墩 事 件 使 得 台 灣 民 眾
that the public voluntarily marched in the streets
第 一 次 自 發 性 上 街 頭
in protest of election fraud,
抗 議 選 舉 舞 弊
and was a prelude to street movements.
揭 開 了 街 頭 運 動 的 序 幕
The opposition had gained momentum
這 股 黨 外 全 國 串 聯 的 力 量
throughout Taiwan.
越 來 越 盛 大
In the public official election in 1978,
延 續 到 1978 年 公 職 人 員 選 舉
opposition candidates
黨 外 參 選 人 的 氣 勢
often drew large, fanatic crowds.
經 常 造 成 洶湧 人 潮 的 狂 熟 氣 氟
The election, however,
但 是 這 次 的 選 舉
was cancelled by Chiang Ching-kuo
卻 在 美 國 宣 布
after the U.S. announced
與 中 華 人 民 共 和 國
that it had established diplomatic ties
建 交 的 衝 擊 下
with the PRC.
被 蔣 經 國 下 令 中 止
After the R.O.C. and the U.S. severed diplomatic ties,
中 美 斷 交 後
U.S. Deputy State Secretary, Warren Christopher,
美 國 副 國 務 卿 克 里 斯 多 福
arrived in Taiwan to discuss issues after the fact.
來 台 協 商 斷 交 善 後 事 宜
Foreign Minister Fred Chien issued a strong statement,
外 交 部 長 錢 復 發 表 嚴 重 聲 明
and the Taiwan people also unleashed strong protests.
台 灣 民 眾 也 展 開 激 烈 的 抗 議
This was yet another enormous setback
這 是 國 民 黨 政 府
in diplomatic relations of the KMT government
繼 退 出 聯 合 國 後
after withdrawal from the U.N.
最 重 大 的 一 次 外 交 挫 敗
This was also a turning point in Taiwan politics.
卻 也 是 台 灣 政 治 史 上 的 轉 捩 點
The opposition
當 時 的 黨 外 人 士
was forced to reassess the situation due to
困 為 這 個 突 然 的 宣 布
the sudden cancellation of the election.
只 得 重 新 佈 局
They discussed counter-strategies.
商 討 回 應 對 篆
On Dec. 25, a senior member of the opposition,
之 後 於 12 月 25 日
Yu Teng-fa,
由 當 時 黨 外 運 動 大 老
led the signing of
余 登 發 領 銜
a declaration on the state of the nation by the opposition.
簽 署 一 份 黨 外 人 士 國 是 宣 言
The declaration stressed
宣 言 內 容 強 調
strong opposition to the use of force by any
堅 決 反 對 任 何 強 權
hegemony to dictate the destiny of the Taiwan people.
以 武 力 來 強 制 台 灣 人 民 的 命 運
The declaration maintained that the future
也 主 張 台 灣 本 來 的 命 運
of Taiwan should be jointly determined
應 該 由 一 千 七 百 萬 人
by its 17 million people.
共 同 來 決 定
The year after the declaration was issued,
這 個 宣 言 宣 布 後 的 第 二 年
on Jan. 21, 1979,
1979 年 1 月 21 日
the KMT arrested Yu Teng-fa
國 民 黨 突 然 以 涉 嫌 叛 亂 的 罪 名
and his son Yu Jui-yen on charges of sedition.
進 捕 余 登 發 與 他 的 兒 孔 余 瑞 言
The arrest prompted the opposition
困 此 引 發 黨 外 人 士
to march in Kaohsiung County
在 高 雄 縣 橋 頭 舉 行
in protest.
遊 行 抗 議 的 事 件
This was the first protest march
這 也 是 黨 外 人 士 的
by the opposition.
第 一 次 示 威 遊 行
Thereafter, the opposition began
之 後 ， 黨 外 人 士
to use outdoor gatherings
開 始 以 室 外 集 會 的 群 眾 路 線
to promote their cause.
推 展 運 動
Street protests became frequent.
造 成 街 頭 風 潮
Two major
當 時 黨 外 陣 營 中
opposition magazines
有 兩 本 重 要 的 雜 誌
started publication in 1979.
分 別 在 1979 年 創 刊
One was The Eighties Magazine.
一 本 是 ﹁ 八 十 年 代 」 雜 誌
The other was Formosa Magazine.
一 本 是 ﹁ 美 麗 島 」 雜 誌
The Formosa Magazine
﹁ 美 麗 島 」 雜 誌
gathered members of the opposition as staff members
以 社 務 委 員 的 形 式
and helped organized the opposition.
組 織 全 國 各 地 的 黨 外 人 士
In fact, the magazine was a rudimentary political party.
在 實 質 上 具 有 政 黨 的 雛 形
It gathered members of the
他 們 網 羅 了
opposition island-wide
全 國 各 地 的 黨 外 人 物
and organized public speeches.
舉 辦 一 場 又 一 場 的 群 眾 演 講 會
Tension between the ruling and the opposition escalated.
朝 野 之 閒 的 對 峙 越 來 越 綺 張
By the end of 1979,
延 續 到 了 1979 年 的 年 底
the Formosa Incident broke out.
終 於 爆 發 了 美 麗 島 事 件
Long live human rights!
人 權 萬 歲
Long live peace!
和 平 萬 歲
We want peace!
我 們 要 和 平
We want human rights!
我 們 要 人 權
Long life human rights!
人 權 萬 歲
Dec. 10, 1979 is
1979 年 12 月 10 日
Human Rights Day
國 際 人 權 日
In that evening,
當 天 瞪 上
members of the opposition assembled in Kaohsiung City
美 麗 島 人 士 如 期 在 高 雄 市
as scheduled to celebrate Human Rights Day.
舉 行 國 際 人 權 日 紀 念 大 會
The administration deployed large contingents of police.
當 局 派 出 大 批 軍 警 嚴 陣 以 待
Shih Ming-de, the coordinator of the assembly,
掌 管 演 講 現 場 的 施 明 德
learned that the assembly ground
在 得 知 原 預 訂 演 講 地 點
had been sealed off by the police
已 經 被 憲 警 封 鎖
and decided to change the speaking venue
於 是 決 定 將 演 講 場 所
to the traffic circle in Hsinhsing District.
改 在 新 興 區 大 圓 環 強 行 舉 行
A large crowd followed
大 批 的 群 真
the opposition leaders.
隨 著 美 麗 島 人 士 的 領 導
With torches in hand,
手 舉 火 把
they marched to the traffic circle.
遊 行 來 到 大 圓 環
During the speech,
演 講 會 展 開 期 間
the police began to encircle the crowd,
大 批 憲 議 部 隊 開 始 包 圍
and gradually forced them into a small circle.
並 且 逐 漸 縮 小 包 圍 國
A confrontation between the police and the crowd ensued.
一 場 議 民 大 衝 突 回 此 爆 發
The entire incident was
這 個 事 件
later referred to as the Formosa Incident
後 來 被 稱 為 美 麗 島 事 件
or Kaohsiung Incident.
或 高 雄 事 件
As a result of the confrontation,
當 天 晚 上 衝 突 的 結 果
official statistics show that
據 官 方 統 計
close to 100 policemen were injured,
約 有 近 百 名 憲 議 受 傷
but there was no reliable number
而 民 眾 受 傷 的 人 數
of the injured civilians.
則 沒 有 可 靠 的 統 計 數 字
After the incident,
事 件 發 生 之 後
at 5 p.m. on Dec. 12,
12 月 12 日 下 午 五 時
Formosa Magazine held a press conference
美 麗 島 雜 誌 社 舉 行 記 者 會
to clarify the events leading to the confrontation.
對 事 件 的 真 相 加 以 說 明
The Magazine believed that the civilians
認 為 當 天 暹 上 的 情 況
were suppressed even before any violence had occurred.
是 本 暴 先 鎮
The police first sealed off the streets,
是 憲 警 人 員 先 封 鎖 道 路
then used tear gas on the civilians.
再 使 用 催 淚 瓦 斯
In early morning of Dec. 13
13 日 清 晨
Law enforcement agency took swift action
治 安 單 位 採 取 霹靂 行 動
and arrested opposition leaders
以 涉 嫌 叛 亂 的 罪 名
on charges of sedition.
建 捕 黨 外 人 士
Those arrested were Chang Chun-hung,Yao Chia-wen,
張 俊 宏 ， 嬉 嘉 文 ， 陳 菊
Chen Chu, Annette Lu, Lin Yi-hsiung, Wang To,
呂 秀 蓮 ， 林 義 雄 ， 王 拓
Yang Ching-chu, Chou Ping-te, Chi Wan-sheng,
楊 青 矗 ， 周 平 德 ， 紀 萬 生
Chen Chung-sin, Wei Ting-chao,
陳 患 俸 ， 魏 廷 朝 ， 張 富 志
Chang Fu-chung, and Chiu Yi-pin.
邢 奕 彬 等 人
Shih Ming-de managed to escape
施 明 德 在 軍 警 擎 門 進 捕 之 前
before the police stormed his residence.
倉 惶 逃 走
That day, a prosecutor from the Garrison Command
當 天 警 總 檢 查 官
closed down Formosa Magazine
並 查 封 美 麗 島 雜 誌 社
and its offices in other places.
及 各 地 服 務 處
On Dec. 14,
12 月 14 日
the Garrison Command wrote to the Legislative Yuan,
警 總 行 文 立 法 院
and upon approval by the Legislative Yuan,
經 立 法 院 表 決 同 意 後
arrested Legislator Huang Hsin-chieh.
進 捕 立 委 黃 俸 介
The Garrison Command subsequently
其 後 ， 警 總 又 陸 續 展 開
arrested scores of people
一 波 波 的 進 捕 行 動
related to the incident.
週 捕 相 關 人 員 約 數 十 人
After 26 days in hiding,
施 明 德 經 過
Shih Ming-de was arrested
二 十 六 天 的 藏 匿 之 後
on Jan. 8 the following year.
也 於 第 二 年 1 月 8 日 被 捕
During that time,
施 明 德 當 時
Shih was branded by the KMT-controlled media
被 國 民 黨 政 府 所 控 制 的 媒 體
as an evil bandit.
宣 傳 成 罪 惡 的 江 洋 大 盎
His picture appeared
他 的 相 片
in newspapers and the television every day.
每 天 出 現 在 報 紙 與 電 視 上
The KMT government also announced
國 民 黨 政 府 並 發 布
huge rewards
高 額 的 懷 賞 獎 金
for his arrest.
他 的 被 捕
Shih's arrest became an international news.
也 困 此 變 成 了 國 際 新 聞 事 件
When Shih was in hiding,
施 明 德 逃 亡 期 間
those who helped and harbored him
南 助 其 逃 亡 並 藏 匿 他 的
including Minister Gao Jyun-ming
台 灣 基 督 長 老 教 會 的
from the Taiwan Presbyterian Church,
高 俊 明 牧 師
Lin Wen-chen, Chang Wun-ying,
以 及 林 文 珍 ， 張 溶 饗
Shih Jui-yun, and Hsu Ching-fu
施 瑞 雲 ， 許 晴 富 ， 許 晴 富 等 多 人
were also arrested for implication.
也 株 連 被 捕
On this Thursday afternoon, a murder occurred
省 議 員 林 義 雄 的 家 裡
at the home of provincial assemblyman Lin Yi-hsiung.
在 這 個 星 期 四 下 午 發 生 凶 殺 案
Lin's 60-year-old mother Yu A-mei
林 義 雄 六 十 歲 的 母 親 游 阿 妹
and 6-year-old twin daughters Lin Liang-chun
和 公 歲 的 雙 生 女 兒
and Lin Ting-chun were murdered.
林 亳 均 ， 林 交 均 這 三 個 人
This was an event that stunned Taiwan.
令 人 震 驚 的 是
It was the morning
正 在 進 行
of the court martial on the Formosa Incident.
美 麗 島 軍 事 大 審 的 期 間
In the morning of Feb. 28, 1980
1980 年 2 月 28 日 上 午
A horrendous murder
省 議 員 林 義 雄 律 師 家 宅
occurred at the home of assemblyman Lin Yi-hsiung.
發 生 慘 絕 人 寰 的 滅 門 大 血 案
Lin's mother and twin daughters
林 母 及 兩 個 雙 生 女 兒
Lin Liang-chun and Lin Ting-chun
林 亳 均 ， 林 亮 均
were murdered by
慮 遭 不 明 身 分 的 凶 手
unknown intruders.
潛 入 家 中 殺 害
Lin Huan-chun, the eldest daughter was seriously hurt.
大 女 兒 林 奐 均 被 殺 成 重 傷
The murders stunned local and overseas communities.
這 件 滅 門 血 案 震 驚 海 內 外
Still hurting from earlier setbacks,
使 得 整 個 黨 外 運 動 在 挫 折 中
the opposition plunged further into deep despair.
更 跌 入 含 傷 的 谷 底
On April 18, 1980,
1980 年 4 月 18 日
the military court of the Taiwan Garrison Command
部 軍 事 法 庭 警 備 總 部
sentenced Shih to life imprisonment,
判 決 施 明 德 無 期 徒 刑
Huang Hsin-chieh to 14 years imprisonment,
黃 俸 介 十 四 年 徒 刑
and Yao Chia-wen,
姚 嘉 文
Chang Chun-hung,
張 俊 宏
Lin Yi-hsiung,
林 義 雁
Annette Lu,
昇 秀 蓮
Chen Chu, and
陳 菊
Lin Hong-hsuan
林 弘 宣
were each sentenced to 12 years in prison.
各 處 有 期 從 刑 十 二 年
The first island-wide crackdown
這 一 次 全 島 性 的 大 搜 捕
on the opposition stunned the nation,
霖 動 全 國
in particular the
尤 其 隨 之 而 來 的
large-scale court martial that followed.
大 規 模 軍 事 審 判
Under pressure from the U.S,
由 於 受 到 美 國 的 壓 力
the trial was made public to the media,
全 面 對 媒 體 開 放
which drew the public's attention.
更 引 起 全 國 的 關 注
The trial started on March 18, 1980,
自 1980 年 3 月 18 日 起
and lasted nine days.
為 期 九 天 的 軍 事 審 判
Each defendant appeared in court and argued about
每 一 位 被 告 在 法 庭 上
the case of the opposition and the future of Taiwan.
對 台 灣 前 途 與 反 對 行 動 的 答 辦
Newspaper reports on the trial
經 由 報 端 披 露 之 後
prompted the public to start
引 起 社 會 大 眾
deliberating Taiwan's political issues,
對 台 灣 政 治 問 題 的 思 考
which unnerved the people even further.
也 造 成 人 心 更 大 的 震 據
On Dec. 6, 1980,
1980 年 12 月 6 日
Election of central government representatives,
囧 名 美 養 T 交 ﹖ 偏 3 篠 呣 年 ﹣ 5 幻
which had been suspended for two years, was resumed.
中 央 民 意 代 表 的 選 舉 恢復 舉 行
In the election,
這 場 選 舉 當 中
opposition candidates,
重 新 出 發 的 黨 外 候 選 人
promised to continue their campaign
以 延 續 黨 外 香 火
and followed the footsteps of their predecessors.
逄 隨 前 著 腳 步
The opposition used this as their campaign theme
為 主 要 的 競 選 訴 求
and were able to win public support.
多 能 得 到 民 眸 的 支 持
Their members were elected through overwhelming votes.
而 高 票 當 選
The opposition
黨 外 勢 力
was thus able to recover,
困 此 從 挫 敗 中 恢復 元 氣
regroup,
重 新 整 合
and enter into a new era.
並 進 入 新 的 階 段
The defense lawyers at the Formosa Incident trial,
美 麗 島 事 件 的 辯 護 律 師 群
Yu Ching, Chiang Peng-chien,
尤 清 # 江 江 鵬 堅
Chen Shui-bian, Frank Hsieh, and Su Chen-chang
陳 水 炳 ， 謝 長 廷 ， 蘇 貞 昌
joined the opposition movement
在 大 審 之 後
after the trial,
也 紛 紛 投 入 政 治 運 動 的 行 列
which rewrote
一 波 波 改 寫 了
Taiwan's political history.
貌 冶 發 展 的 風 台 灣 政 治
After the Formosa Incident,
美 麗 島 事 件 之 後
the democracy movement gained momentum.
民 主 潮 流 風 起 雲 湧
Democracy in Taiwan
台 灣 的 民 主
reverberated and spread
反 而 透 過 選 舉 政 治 與 街 頭 運 動
through elections and street movements.
不 斷 的 激 盪 ， 展 開
The Taiwan people
台 灣 人 民
started to use election and street demonstrations,
一 方 面 透 過 選 舉 與 街 頭 運 動
to overcome political taboos.
突 破 政 治 禁 恥
Social movements
各 種 社 會 運 動
such as consumers protection movement
像 是 消 費 者 保 護 運 動
and the anti-Dupont demonstration in Lukang
和 鹿 港 的 反 杜 邦 遊 行
initiated civilian action of environmental protection.
也 開 啟 了 民 間 環 保 抗 議 的 行 動
This was followed by the women's rights movement,
接 著 而 來 的 婦 女 運 動
labor movement, student movement,
工 人 運 動 ， 學 生 運 動
veterans returning home movement,
老 兵 返 鄉 運 動
to the subsequent farmers' movement.
到 後 來 的 農 民 運 動
The forces of resistance
這 種 種 反 抗 力 量
continued to surge.
一 時 之 間 風 起 雲 湧
The waves of people power
這 一 波 波 人 民 力 量 的 展 現
that resulted in massive protests
所 爆 發 的 激 烈 拔 爭
shook Taiwan.
都 震 擊 了 全 國 百 姓
The potential for social movement
台 灣 原 住 民 蓄 積 已 久 的
long bottled up inside the indigenous people,
社 會 運 動 潛 力
at this point
到 此 時
gushed like water
也 姜 同 水 庫 開 啟 閔 門 的 水
rushing out an open dam.
奎 流 而 出
From the Kaoshan Ching Magazine
從 早 期 的 ﹁ 高 山 青 」 雜 誌 開 始
to the Commission for the Promotion of Rights of
到 1984 年 成 立
Indigenous Peoples established in 1984, young
原 住 民 權 利 促 進 委 員 會
indigenous intellectuals
原 住 民 知 識 青 年
started a series of protests
展 開 了 一 連 串 的 抗 爭 運 動
in an attempt to rediscover
試 圖 找 回
their traditional culture that had been lost
在 遭 受 經 濟 與 文 化 衝 擊 之 下
due to economic and cultural impacts,
那 早 已 失 落 的 傳 統 文 化
and to rediscover their own identity.
與 對 自 己 族 群 的 認 同
On Sept. 28, 1986,
1986 年 9 月 28 日
The Opposition Campaign Assistance Group
黨 外 中 央 後 援 會
convened at the Grand Hotel in Taipei
在 台 北 圓 山 飯 店
to nominate its candidates.
召 開 候 選 人 推 薦 會 時
The Group decided to form the
決 議 以 黨 外 候 選 人
Democratic Progressive Party (DPP) with the
為 共 同 發 起 人
opposition candidates as founding members.
正 式 成 立 民 主 進 步 黨
The establishment of the DPP was an unprecedented
向 厲 行 黨 禁 達 四 十 年 的
challenge to the KMT administration,
國 民 黨 當 局
which had banned political parties for four decades.
做 歷 史 性 挑 戰
New hope for democracy.
民 主 新 希 望
New political party to save Taiwan.
新 黨 敕 台 灣
Since the establishment of the DPP
從 民 主 進 步 黨
in 1986,
成 立 的 1986 年 起
many political taboos of the past
許 多 過 去 的 政 治 禁 恒
started to shatter.
紛 紛 被 突 破
On May 19,
從 5 月 19 日
Cheng Nan-jung started
鄭 南 槎 等 人 發 動 群 眾
his sit-down protest in Lungshan Temple
在 龍 山 寺 靜 坐
to demand the lifting of martial rule.
要 求 解 除 戒 嚴 開 始
Many crowd protests, demonstrations,
各 種 群 眾 抗 議 ， 示 姥
appeals, self-help movements,
請 願 ， 自 力 救 濟
and street marches appeared.
街 頭 遊 行 的 活 動 層 出 不 窮
Our response to the international...
我 們 困 應 國 際 的 …
The elderly Chiang Ching-kuo,
年 邁 的 蔣 經 國
realizing that political freedom was inevitable, made
體 察 政 治 閘 放 已 經 無 可 避 免
an important announcement within the KMT.
在 黨 內 做 出 重 大 宣 示
On July 14, 1987,
1987 年 7 月 14 日
President Chiang officially ordered
蔣 經 國 總 統 正 式 發 布 命 令
the lifting of martial rule in Taiwan
宣 告 台 灣 自 15 日 零 時 起
starting July 15.
解 除 戒 嚴
On July 14,
7 月 14 日
The Legislative Yuan announced that martial rule
准 立 法 院 宣 告 台 灣 地 區
would be lifted starting July 15,1987.
自 76 年 7 月 15 日 零 時 起 解 嚴
Mr. President...
總 統 …
Waves after waves of civil movement
一 波 又 一 波 的 人 民 運 動
finally put an end
終 於 衝 開 了
to the world's longest martial rule.
全 世 界 實 施 最 久 的 戒 嚴 令
After 38-years of martial rule,
解 除 長 達 38 年 的 戒 嚴 之 後
the ban on citizens to visit relatives in China
其 他 姐 開 放 大 陸 探 親
and the newspaper ban were also lifted.
解 除 報 禁 等 等
Taiwan was finally able to implement true democracy
讓 台 灣 實 施 真 正 民 主 的 制 度
and take a giant stride forward.
大 步 邁 開
In 1988,
1988 年
Chiang, who had long suffered from diabetes,
長 年 飽 受 糖 尿 病 之 苺 的 蔣 經 國
passed away at 3:50 p.m.
最 後 在 1 月 13 日
on Jan. 13.
下 午 三 點 五 十 分 病 逝
Vice-president Lee Teng-hui
總 統 宣 誓
was duly sworn in as the
副 總 統 李 登 輝
7th president of the R.O.C.
依 法 繼 任 中 華 民 國 第 七 任 總 統
I pledged my allegiance
余 謹 以 至 該
to the people of Taiwan...
向 全 國 人 民 宣 誓
Lee was born in Sanchih Township, Taipei County.
出 生 於 台 北 縉 三 芝 鄉 的 李 登 輝
While he was studying at the Kyoto Imperial University,
就 讀 日 本 京 都 帝 國 大 學 時
Japan lost the war with China.
日 本 戰 敗
Lee later studied agriculture economics at NTU.
糠 學 回 台 大 農
As a scholar of agriculture economics,
為 農 經 學 者 出 身
he was groomed by Chiang Ching-kuo
在 蔣 經 國 的 提 拔 下
and served as minister without portfolio
一 路 由 行 政 院 政 務 委 員
and later, vice-president.
提 升 到 副 總 統
After Lee became president,
但 是 李 登 輝 在 繼 任 總 統 後
public demand for reform
立 即 面 臨 來 自 民 閒
increased.
更 多 更 強 燒 的 改 革 要 求
In January 1989,
1989 年 1 月
Cheng Nan-jung, who once launched the 519 Green Action
曾 發 起 五 一 九 緞 色 行 動
to promote total freedom of speech
推 動 百 分 之 百 言 論 自 由 的
and founder of Freedom Era Weekly,
自 由 時 代 雜 誌 創 辦 人 鄭 南 榕
published the new Taiwan constitution
困 刊 登 許 世 楷 教 授 的
drafted by Prof. Hsu Shih-kai
台 灣 新 憲 法 草 案
and was charged with insurrection
遭 統 治 當 局
by the government.
控 以 涉 嫌 叛 亂 的 罪 名
Cheng refused to appear in court,
鄭 南 榖 拒 絕 出 庭 應 訊
and confined himself in the
於 是 在 雜 誌 社
publishing office for 71 days.
展 開 長 達 七 十 一 天 的 自 囚 行 動
On April 7, the police
4 月 7 日
surrounded the publishing office ready to arrest him.
大 批 警 察 包 圍 雜 誌 社 準 備 拘 提
Cheng lighted the gasoline he had prepared in advance
鄭 南 榕 點 燃 旱 已 準 備 好 的 汽 油
and set himself on fire.
引 火 自 焚
His self-immolation stunned the nation.
霖 驕 全 國
During Cheng's farewell rites on May 19,
5 月 19 日
the procession reached
鄭 南 榕 的 告 別 式
the Office of the President,
以 遊 行 到 總 統 府 的 方 式 舉 行
and the spirit of opposition movement
台 灣 反 對 運 動 的 民 氣
in Taiwan reached its peak.
遮 到 壯 烈 的 頂 點
This was a test for the new president Lee.
更 考 驗 著 才 剛 上 任 的 李 登 輝
This same year, the Berlin Wall fell
這 一 年 ， 柏 林 圍 牆 倒 塌
and the Cold War ended.
東 西 方 冷 戰 返 速 結 束
A new world order had begun.
開 啟 了 世 界 的 新 秣 序
A new order was starting to take shape in Taiwan.
台 灣 的 新 秣 序 也 在 重 整 中
In 1990,
1990 年
A faction within the KMT refused to
國 民 黨 內 部 的 一 部 分 勤 力
accept Lee's leadership and policy.
並 本 接 受 李 登 輝 的 領 導 與 路 線
In February 1990, during the election of the 8th president
1990 年 2 月
at the National Assembly, which was composed of
以 老 代 表 為 主 的 國 民 大 會
representatives elected on the mainland,
選 舉 第 八 任 總 統
confrontation between Lee and the non-mainstream faction erupted.
爆 發 非 主 流 派 對 李 登 輝 的 抗 衡
This was the political infighting in February 1988.
此 即 二 月 政 爭
Also, the National Assembly passed the amendment to
再 回 國 民 大 會 通 過
the Temporary Provisions, which extended the tenure
蟹 時 條 款 修 正 案
of the National Assembly representatives.
延 甘 國 大 代 表 的 任 期
The amendment contradicted the people's will
這 個 運 反 民 意
and gave more power to the representatives.
恣 意 擴 權 的 法 案
Thus, it led to the March 1990 Student Movement.
引 發 了 三 月 學 運
Dissolve the National Assembly!
解 散 國 民 大 會
Abolish the Temporary Provisions!
廢 除 臨 時 條 款
Convene a national affairs conference!
召 開 國 是 會 議
In March 1990,
1990 年 3 月
thousands of college students
數 千 名 大 專 院 校 學 生
gathered for a sit-down at the CKS Memorial Hall
集 中 在 中 正 紀 念 堂 靜 坐
to protest the abuse of power by the National Assembly.
抗 議 國 民 大 會 濫 權
The students demanded that the National Assembly
要 求 解 散 國 會
be dissolved, the Temporary Provisions be abolished,
廢 除 臨 時 條 款
a national affairs conference be convened,
召 開 國 是 會 議
and a timetable for reform be presented
提 出 改 革 時 間 表
in respond to the people's will.
以 呼 廳 民 意 潮 流
The students sat for five days,
學 生 持 續 靜 坐 的 第 五 天
and President Lee officially met
李 登 輝 總 統 正 式
with the student representatives.
與 學 生 代 表 會 談
The day after the meeting, the student movement
會 談 之 後 的 第 二 天
coordinating center issued a statement to withdrawal,
學 運 指 揮 中 心 宣 布
stressing its “unrelenting pursuit for democracy,”
逄 求 民 主 永 不 懈 怠 的 撤 退 聲 明
The 6-day student movement thus ended.
結 束 為 期 六 天 的 三 月 學 運 抗 爭
In June 28, 1990,
1990 年 6 月 28 日
in response to the students' demands, a national affairs
困 應 三 月 學 運 的 訴 求
conference was convened at the Grand Hotel.
國 是 會 議 在 圓 山 飯 店 召 開
A consensus was reached to promote reform of the
達 成 共 識
National Assembly and direct election of the president.
依 序 推 動 國 會 改 革 及 總 統 民 選
An further announcement was made to terminate the Period
之 後 進 一 步 宣 告
of Mobilization for the Suppression of Rebellion.
依 法 終 止 動 員 戡 亂 時 期
The Period of Mobilization for the Suppression of
依 法 宣 告
Rebellion was terminated in accordance with law.
終 止 動 員 戡 亂 時 期
On Dec. 3, 1994,
1994 年 12 月 3 日
the Constitution was amended to allow for direct elections
台 灣 在 修 憲 後
of the provincial governor and city mayors.
第 一 次 開 放 省 市 首 長 直 選
In the meantime, investments
同 一 個 時 期
of Taiwanese businessmen in China were increasing as lots
台 商 對 中 國 大 陸 投 資 明 顳 增 加
of capital from Taiwan moved into mainland China.
台 灣 的 資 金 大 量 湧 向 中 國 大 陸
Despite cross-Strait
兩 岸 之 間
political and military stalemate,
政 治 與 軍 事 長 期 僵 持 不 下
cross-Strait trade and cultural exchanges
但 是 經 貴 活 動 與 文 化 交 流
increased rapidly after the 1990s.
卻 在 1990 年 代 之 後 高 度 發 展
The situation was ironic.
實 在 是 一 種 非 常 矛 盾 的 狀 慈
Communist China, which claimed peaceful emergence,
自 稱 和 平 螈 起 的 共 產 中 國
was alien to the Taiwan people.
對 台 灣 人 民 而 言 是 極 為 陌 生 的
China was a socialist society that went through Cultural
那 是 一 個 經 過 文 化 大 革 命
Revolution and was actively seeking modernization.
和 積 極 現 代 化 的 社 會 主 義 中 國
Likewise, Taiwan awareness,
同 樣 的 ， 台 灣 意 識 的 覺 醒
which originated from the island's history
源 自 於 台 灣 本 身
of immigrants and colonizers,
所 經 歷 的 移 民 和 殖 民 的 歷 史
was also incomprehensible to China.
也 是 對 岸 難 以 完 全 了 解 的
In June 1995,
1995 年 6 月
Lee Teng-hui's speech in the U.S.
李 登 輝 赴 美 發 表 演 說
attracted international attention.
引 起 國 際 社 會 高 度 關 注
In 1996, Taiwan finally held
1996 年 台 灣 終 於 舉 行
its first direct presidential election.
有 史 以 來 第 一 次 總 統 民 選
In the run-up to the election,
選 舉 期 間
China conducted a series of missile tests
中 國 向 台 灣 島 的 邊 緣 海 域
in the vicinity of the Taiwan Strait.
發 射 飛 彈
Cross-strait tension was at its peak
飛 彈 危 機 造 成 台 灣 海 峽
since the end of the Cold War.
自 冷 戰 結 束 後 的 最 緊 張 對 峙
During the 1996 presidential election,
在 1996 年 的 總 統 選 舉 期 間
the KMT became officially divided.
國 民 黨 也 正 式 分 裂
Then incumbent President Lee Teng-hui
由 當 時 擔 任 總 統 的 李 登 輝
and then Premier Lien Chan
與 當 時 的 行 政 院 長 連 戰
represented the KMT in the election.
代 表 參 選
Yet two KMT vice chairmen left the party
但 是 兩 位 國 民 黨 副 主 席
and ran in the election with support from the New Party.
則 脫 黨 由 新 黨 支 持 參 選
The DPP for the first time also presented its candidates
民 主 進 步 黨 也 首 次 推 出
for president and vice-president.
正 副 總 統 候 選 人 參 選
Furthermore,
另 外
independent candidates
沒 有 政 黨 奧 援 的 社 會 人 士
also ran in the election.
也 參 與 競 爭
During the election,
選 舉 期 間
despite China's
對 岸 的 中 國
military exercises aimed at Taiwan,
對 台 灣 進 行 模 擬 的 軍 事 演 習
Taiwan responded with
但 是 台 灣 人 民 仍 以 高 達
a 76 percent voter turnout,
百 分 之 七 十 六 的 投 票 率
with more than 14 million voters
共 有 超 過 一 千 四 百 萬 選 民
casting their ballots.
投 下 神 聖 的 一 票
Lee Teng-hui became
李 登 輝 獲 選 為
the first popularly elected president.
第 一 任 的 民 選 總 統
In over thousands of years,
這 是 數 千 年 來
this was an unprecedented feat
所 有 華 人 治 理 國 家 之 中
in countries governed by Chinese people.
前 所 未 有 的 成 就
In 2000,
2000 年
the direct presidential election made possible
台 灣 人 民 也 透 過 選 舉
the first-ever transition of political power in Taiwan.
完 成 第 一 次 的 政 黨 輪 替
DPP candidate Chen Shui-bian
民 進 黨 籍 的 陳 水 岡
was elected the 10th president
以 相 對 多 數 票
by a relative majority.
當 選 第 十 任 總 統
This was the first transition
開 創 了 台 灣 首 度 的
of political power in Taiwan,
政 黨 輪 替 執 政
signaling the end of
政 黨 輪 替 也 象 徵 了
the single-party leadership
台 灣 向 過 去 的
in place in Taiwan for many years.
一 黨 獨 大 政 治 告 別
The DPP victory prevented the further decline in Taiwan
擺 脫 向 下 沉 淪 的 力 量
and allowed infusion of new energy to provide the people
謝 詰 涯 2 讓 清 流 共 治 向 上 提 升
with a clean and fair political environment.
還 給 人 民 一 個 清 明 的 政 治 環 境
In 2001,
2001 年
Taiwan was listed among the nations in
美 國 人 權 組 織 自 由 之 家
Freedom in the World,
公 布 的 世 界 自 由 地 圖 中
published by human rights organization Freedom House.
台 灣 也 正 式 躋身 其 中
Taiwan was marked green in its
在 瞎 徵 完 全 自 由 國 家 的
Map of Freedom, along with
緞 色 地 圖 上
the U.K, Japan, France, and Germany.
與 莫 日 法 德 等 國 並 列
Taiwan has continued to press forward
台 灣 繼 續 在 民 主 的 道 路 上
along the path of democracy.
向 前 挺 進
Over the past 20 to 30 years in Taiwan,
台 灣 在 近 二 ， 三 在 近 二 ， 三 十 年 的
political reform and transformation
政 治 改 革 與 轉 型
have resulted in
在 民 主 的 形 式 上
tangible democratic achievements.
有 一 定 的 成 總
Yet there remained much room for improvement in
但 在 民 主 運 作 的 實 質 內 涵 上
its democratic institutions.
仍 有 相 當 的 改 革 空 間
These include regulations on party politics,
例 如 政 黨 競 爭 的 規 範
quality of the legislation,
國 會 政 治 的 品 質
improvements in the election culture,
選 舉 文 化 的 提 升
and upgrade of the education system.
教 育 制 度 的 改 善 等 等
These are challenges facing
這 些 都 是 台 灣 人 民
the Taiwan people in the future.
未 來 必 須 面 臨 的 挑 戰
In Sept. 21, 1999, Taiwan was hit with the
1999 年 的 9 月 21 日
largest earthquake in the last century.
台 灣 發 生 近 百 年 來 最 大 的 地 震
Measuring 7.3 on the Richter scale,
這 個 規 模 高 達
the earthquake shook
茵 氏 7﹒3 級 的 強 震
the entire island late in the evening.
在 深 夜 震 據 全 島
Many victims were buried by debris
許 多 民 眾 在 睡 夢 中
in their sleep.
被 埋 在 震 垮 的 瓦 礫 堆 當 中
Damage was specially serious
尤 其 是 位 於 震 央 的 中 部 地 區
at the epicenter in central Taiwan.
災 情 最 為 嚴 重
Over 2,330 people died
全 國 共 計 有
in the tremor.
兩 千 三 百 三 十 餘 人 罹 難
The earthquake
這 個 地 震
totally or partially destroyed
造 成 全 國 一 萬 間 以 上 的 房 子
over 10,000 houses,
全 倒 或 半 倒
leaving more than 100,000 people homeless.
使 得 十 萬 多 人 無 家 可 歸
Many public buildings were also damaged.
並 且 有 許 多 棟 公 共 建 築 物 損 毀
The disaster area extended from
災 區 的 範 圍
Taipei in the north to Chiayi in the south.
北 至 台 北 ， 南 達 嘉 義
The quake was the worst natural disaster
可 說 是 台 灣 是 台 灣 有 史 以 來
and the most damaging
損 失 最 嚴 重
in Taiwan's history.
夷 區 最 大 的 一 次 天 然 災害
After the earthquake,
大 地 震 之 後
the government and civilians worked jointly
政 府 與 民 間 攜 手 投 入 救 災
in relief and recovery.
努 力 共 同 度 遇 危 難
Donations from the private sector reached NT$20 billion.
民 間 捐 款 短 期 內 即 達 到 兩 百 億
Relief goods from all over Taiwan
而 各 種 救 援 物 資
flowed into the disaster areas.
從 台 灣 各 地 湧 入 災 區
People from all walks of life
不 同 行 業 的 台 灣 百 姓
volunteered in the disaster areas.
大 批 進 入 災 區 擔 任 志 工
They worked together with the military and rescue personnel,
與 軍 人 ， 救 災 人 員 攜 手
digging and pulling survivors from the debris,
從 瓦 礫 堆 中 挖 授 生 還 者
and finding places for the victims to stay.
並 且 安 置 灸 氏
The 921 earthquake brought out the goodness
九 二 一 大 地 震
and compassion of the Taiwan people.
具 體 展 現 了 台 灣 人 民 善 良 熟 情
People joined hands
攜 手 互 助
to subsist the crisis with a steadfast attitude.
共 度 難 關 的 堅 怒 性 格
In a few years,
短 短 幾 年 間
reconstruction work has been mostly completed.
災 區 重 建 工 作 也 大 多 完 成
After the 1990s,
1990 年 代 開 始
Taiwan experienced another
台 灣 在 經 濟 上
economic breakthrough.
也 進 一 步 蛻 變
The business sector and the KMT government
金 業 界 與 國 民 黨 政 府
actively promoted IT applications.
積 極 推 展 資 訊 科 技 的 懋 用
Taiwan transformed from a major IT manufacturer
台 灣 又 從 資 訊 產 業 大 國
to a major player in IT applications.
變 成 資 訊 應 用 大 國
Taiwan has finally entered the IT Age.
真 正 進 入 資 訊 時 代
Inspired by the success of
由 於 新 竹 科 學 園 區
the Hsinchu Science-based Industrial Park,
優 異 成 果 的 鼓 舞
the Tainan Science-based Industrial Park and
台 南 科 學 園 區
the Taichung Science-based Industrial Park
台 中 科 學 園 區
were established in
也 紛 紛 於 1998， 2003 年
1998 and 2003.
簸 備 成 立
New industrial parks would transform and upgrade
希 望 藉 此 帶 動 中 南 部
manufacturing industry in central and northern Taiwan.
台 灣 製 造 業 的 轉 型 與 升 級
In recent years, the development of private brands
近 幾 年 開 發 自 有 品 牌
has become the trend in the IT industry.
也 成 了 資 訊 業 最 新 的 趨 勢
Many subcontract manufacturers
許 多 代 工 形 態 的 廠 商
have undergone successful transformation
也 成 功 轉 型
and created their own brand names.
並 且 自 創 品 牌
At present, Taiwan is the world's third largest
目 前 台 灣 是 第 ﹁ 台 灣 是 世 界 第 三 大
IT products exporter.
資 訊 科 技 產 品 輸 出 國
More than half of the computers worldwide
全 世 界 有 一 半 以 上 的 電 腦
are manufactured in Taiwan.
都 有 台 灣 的 胎 記
Taiwan accounts for more than 70 percent of
全 球 七 成 以 上 晶 圓 代 工 市 場
the global foundry business.
由 台 灣 獨 占
Taiwan is now
台 灣 已 經 是
a major player in the IT industry.
名 副 其 實 的 資 訊 大 國
Apart from the IT industry,
資 訊 產 業 之 外
advancements in the traditional industries have
許 多 傳 統 產 業 也 精 益 求 精
resulted in the creation of private brand products that
逐 漸 建 立 自 創 品 牌
are successfully exported to the international market.
並 且 成 功 行 銷 國 際
From bicycle to textile industries,
自 自 行 車 到 紡 織 業
from butterfly orchids to fine china,
從 蝴 蝶 蘭 到 精 緻 的 瓷 器
as well as Chinese glass art,
與 創 意 瑯 璃
they are all internationally well-known.
都 有 顯 著 的 國 際 名 聲
Despite limited natural resources,
缺 乏 天 然 資 源 的 台 灣
Taiwan has relied on the efforts of the government
憑 著 政 府 與 民 間 的 多 年 努 力
and private sector to rank number 5
2005 年 的 全 球 競 爭 力
in global competition in 2005.
排 名 第 五
Taiwan is the world's 17th largest economy,
是 全 球 第 十 七 大 經 濟 體
and the 16th largest trading country.
第 十 六 大 貿 易 國
Taiwan's GDP ranks 20th in the world.
國 民 生 產 毛 額 居 世 界 第 二 十 位
Geographically,
打 開 世 界 地 國
the small island of Taiwan is not really that small.
小 小 的 台 灣 其 實 並 不 小
It has an area larger than those of
國 土 面 積 比 百 分 之 四 十 的
40 percent of U.N. member countries.
聯 合 國 會 員 國 選 大
Taiwan's 23 million population
而 人 口 兩 千 三 百 萬
is larger than those of
甚 至 超 過 了
three-fourths of the U.N. member countries.
聯 合 國 四 分 之 三 的 國 家
This country,
這 樣 的 國 家
whether referred to as Taiwan or Republic of China, has not
不 論 被 稱 為 台 灣 或 中 華 民 國
received fairly treatment from the global community
一 直 沒 有 被 全 世 界 公 平 的 對 待
to become member of world organizations.
也 無 法 成 為 國 際 組 織 的 一 分 子
But just like in previous generations,
不 過 就 妒 同 歷 代 先 民
the people of Taiwan remain undeterred and resilient.
在 遇 去 歲 月 中 的 強 韌 與 打 拼
The people of Taiwan will not lose hope
台 灣 人 民 雖 然 常 處 在 逆 境 之 中
even in adverse situations.
卻 也 不 曾 放 棄 希 望
Taiwan's democracy and economic development
台 灣 的 民 主 政 治 與 經 濟 發 展
will continue to meet challenges.
顯 然 仍 將 接 受 試 煉
But the people of Taiwan, unwavering in its pursuit,
但 打 拼 精 神 昂 揚 的 台 灣 人 民
will choose no other alternatives
沒 有 選 擇
but to resolutely move toward the future.
只 脊 堅 定 奔 向 未 來